<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Christ's-Church, Dublin, November 18, 1693 at the funeral of His Grace Francis Lord Archbishop of Dublin / by the Reverend Father in God Anthony, Lord Bishop of Meath.</title>
            <author>Dopping, Anthony, 1643-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16292382</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16292382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105264</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36346)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1090:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Christ's-Church, Dublin, November 18, 1693 at the funeral of His Grace Francis Lord Archbishop of Dublin / by the Reverend Father in God Anthony, Lord Bishop of Meath.</title>
                  <author>Dopping, Anthony, 1643-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray ... and are to be sold by the booksellers of Dublin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marsh, Francis, 1627-1693.</term>
               <term>Church of Ireland --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105264:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN CHRIST's-CHURCH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN</hi> NOVEMBER 18. 1693. AT THE FUNERAL Of His GRACE FRANCIS Lord Archbishop of DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>By the Reverend Father in GOD, ANTHONY Lord Biſhop of MEATH.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray</hi> on <hi>College Green,</hi> and are to be Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>Dublin.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:105264:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105264:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>II COR. V. 1.</bibl>
               <q>For we know that if our Earthly Houſe of this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle were Diſſolved, we have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Words that I have read unto you, are a Reaſon render'd by the Apoſtle of ſomething before diſcourſed of; and if we look into the preceding Chapter, we ſhall find that he is there rendring an Account of his Sufferings for the Goſpel, and his chearful Submiſſion to thoſe Sufferings, on the hopes of being better Rewarded in another World. It was the Contemplation of thoſe Eternal Joys which <hi>God hath prepared for thoſe that love Him,</hi> that made him run through ſo many Dangers, and endure ſuch a Numerous Train of Misfortunes, with ſo Heroick and Undaunted a Courage as he did. That made the Primitive Chriſtians deſpiſe the Swords and the Axes, the Racks and the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of their Perſecutors; that taught them to ſing in the midſt of the moſt ſcorching Flames, and expire in the midſt of the moſt cruel Torments, with as much Serenity and Unconcernedneſs as if they had been Repoſing themſelves on a Bed of Roſes. For <hi>they had an Eye to the Recompence of</hi> a <hi>Reward</hi> hereafter, and were as certain of enjoying it as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105264:3"/> if they had it in actual poſſeſſion: They look'd upon all their Sorrows and Afflictions as light and eaſie, in reſpect of that <hi>far more exceeding and eternal Weight of Glory</hi> that was ready to Crown all their Labours, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> IV. 17. They <hi>look'd not at the things that were ſeen,</hi> which were able to affright them with the Terror of their Appearance; but <hi>at the things which were not ſeen,</hi> at that inviſible ſtate of Joy and Comfort, which was abundantly ſufficient to comfort and refreſh their Spirits in the height of their greateſt Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. And when their Perſecutors were tormenting of their Bodies, and exerciſing all the Cruelty upon them that the Wit and Rage of an Enemy could invent, they were ſo far from ſhrinking back, or complaining under their Pains, that they looked upon them as an haſtening of their Joys, and an Emancipation of their Souls from the dark and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Priſon of their Bodies: Being well aſſured that <hi>when the Earthly Houſe of their Tabernacle was Diſſolved; they had a Building of God prepared for them, an Houſe not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>Earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle,</hi> we are to un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand the frail and mortal Body of Man, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calls an <hi>Earthly Houſe,</hi> and a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> becauſe of its ſimilitude to them. It is compared to an Houſe, becauſe it is the Habitation of the Soul that is lodged within it, our Bodies being only given us for the Entertainment of our Souls, and the more eaſie exerciſe of their Operations: And ſo much the <hi>Stoicks</hi> have inſtructed us out of their Philoſophy, whilſt they compare the Body to a Casket, but the Soul to a rich and pretious Jewel that is lodged within it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is called an <hi>Earthly Houſe,</hi> becauſe it was firſt framed out of the Duſt of the Earth, and muſt again return to its firſt Principle; and it is reſembled to a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> not only in Conformity to the Phraſe and Idiom of the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> who do frequently call it ſo in their Writings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105264:3"/> but alſo becauſe of its Mutability &amp; Uncertainty, it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Tabernacle to be removed from place to place; and it is the Nature and Conſtitution of our Bodies to be ſubject to Changes, and at laſt diſſolved and pulled in pieces. By the <hi>Houſe not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> we are to underſtand that ſtate of Dignity and Immortality to which our Bodies ſhall be advanced in another World, which is therefore called <hi>a Building of God,</hi> becauſe it is of his ordering and preparing. <hi>An Houſe not made with Hands,</hi> becauſe not ſubject to Changes and Decays, and it is called <hi>Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> to denote the place and the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of it, our Immortal Bodies ſhall be placed in Heaven, and ſhall be no more ſubject to Diſſolution or Corruption.</p>
            <p>So that the ſence of the Words may be explain'd by this ſhort Paraphraſe: We Chriſtians do certainly know that our Bodies ſhall be Diſſolved into Duſt and Aſhes, and we do not in the leaſt doubt but that after their Diſſolution they ſhall be raiſed up again to a ſtate of Immortality and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, and placed in the Heavens, where they ſhall no more be ſubject to Decays and Alterations. From the Words thus Explain'd, I ſhall raiſe theſe following Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That theſe Bodies that we carry about us are only the Outward Shell or Covering of ſome more Excellent Thing that is lodged within them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they ſhall be Diſſolved, and pull'd in pieces.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That after their Diſſolution, they are not to remain Eternally Rotting in the Graves, but ſhall be Advanced to a better ſtate than they enjoyed before, to a ſtate of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality and Eternal Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Place or State in which they ſhall be fixed, is the Heavens above.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we Chriſtians have the higheſt Reaſons, and the ſtrongeſt Arguments to induce us to believe all this, for we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105264:4"/> know and are aſſured, That when <hi>the Earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle is Diſſolved, we have a Building of God an Houſe not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. I bgin with the firſt particular, That our Bodies are only the Outward Shell or Covering of ſome more Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Thing that is lodged within them. For the proof of this, I ſhall only inſiſt on ſuch Arguments as do ariſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally out of the Text: They are here compared to an <hi>Houſe</hi> and a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> now the Notion of an <hi>Houſe,</hi> doth imply ſome Perſon or another that is to inhabit it, no Man being ſo Unreaſonable as to Erect it, but with a reſpect to this End, and out of a Deſign to fit it for the Conveniencies of ſome to dwell in it. And the Notion of a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> doth imply the ſame thing, and direct us to the ſame Sence and Meaning: We read in the Old Teſtament of the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Teſtament,</hi> and of <hi>the Tabernacles of the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds,;</hi> the former directs us to the Preſence of God that was pleaſed to dwell in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and for whoſe Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it was Erected; And the latter points us to the End and Uſe for which thoſe Tabernacles were Erected, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, For the Conveniencies of the Shepherds that were to lodge in them. It is ſo likewiſe in the ſtate and condition of theſe mortal Bodies that God hath given to the Sons of Men, which are only prepared for the Receptacle of our Souls, to be an Help meet and convenient for them, and to ſerve as a ready Organ or Inſtrument of their Actions.</p>
            <p>When Almighty God breathed into the Firſt Man the Breath of Life, and quickned the firſt Lump of Clay with an Active Principle of Heat and Motion, it was none of his Deſign that Men ſhould fall in love with the Beauty of their own Faces, or the neat Contexture of their Parts. This were in effect to place our Affections on things below them, and make an Idol of our ſelves; we ſhould rather conſider that all this Symmetry and Proportion of Parts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105264:4"/> the Activity of our Bodies, and the Strength of our Limbs, and the admirable Order and Proportion of all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Body, were principally given us for the Uſe and Convenience of that Ray of Himſelf, that <hi>Divinae Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae Particula,</hi> that he was reſolved to place in ſo fair a Pile of Building. And from thence we ſhould deſcend to an Admiration of his Wiſdom and Providence in the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, and conclude with our ſelves, That when he made us after his own Image and Similitude, by placing an Immortal Soul within us, that it was our incumbent Duty, not only to honour that Divine Gueſt which he ſent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit it; but alſo to take a care of treating it with as much Ceremony and Reſpect as men do the richeſt Jewels in their Cabinet. Let the Conſideration therefore of this Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, prevail with you, my Brethren, to prefer your Souls before your Bodies, to look upon them as more Valuable, and more Uſeful; and conſequently to ſpend more of your Care and Time in the Salvation of your Souls (which are ſo precious in the Eyes of God) than in the Adorning of your Bodies, or the vain purſuits of the Delights and Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fits of the World.</p>
            <p>2. But becauſe this Propoſition is only implied in the Text, I ſhall therefore enlarge no longer on it, but proceed to the next Particular, That theſe Bodies ſhall be Diſſolved and pull'd in pieces. The Similitudes that the Apoſtle makes uſe of, do import as much, for he calls them <hi>Houſes of Clay,</hi> and <hi>Earthly Tabernacles;</hi> by the one referring to their Original, by the other to the Uncertainty of their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Had he barely compared theſe Bodies of ours unto <hi>Houſes,</hi> we might perhaps flatter our ſelves with ſome vain Confidence and Expectation of their more laſting Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; for as ſome Houſes have been obſerved to out-laſt the Violences of Wind and Weather, ſo ſome Perſons might perhaps preſume upon a more long Continuance and Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105264:5"/> of their Bodies. But when it is conſidered that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts them no better than <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> and <hi>Houſes of Clay</hi> or Earth, this alone is an Affrighting Conſideration to the Carnal Man, and a Dreadful Allay to all his Mirth and Jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: For by theſe Similitudes he deſigns to inform us that there is a Principle of Corruption within our Bodies that will bring them to Decay, tho' no Exterior Accident ſhould conſpire to deſtroy them. That they molder and decay every moment, and are in a conſtant progreſs to a Change: That they have not only an Internal Principle of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hurries them to their Ruine, but that they are ſubject to the Will of Almighty God, who removes them from place to place, as the Shepherds do their Tabernacles: That we have no abiding City in this World, but are toſſed about like a Ship in the Sea, and become the Sport and Paſtime of every wanton Wave: That in the midſt of Life, we are in Death; and when we think our ſelves moſt Secure, then Danger is at hand: That our Lives are not at our own Diſpoſal, nor is it in the power of our hands to preſerve theſe Bodies from Sickneſs and Diſtempers: For they are either ſent upon us by the hand of God, or we invite them to our ſelves by our own Riot and Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and when the Phyſician comes to cure our Diſtemper, he unhappily miſtakes the Diſeaſe, and haſtens his Patient to his long home. Thus every thing almoſt, either in Art or Nature, by a ſecret and undiſcernable Hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, contributes to the Diſſolution of our Tabernacle; and whilſt we look for Life, <hi>he turns it into the ſhadow of Death, and makes it groſs Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not, I hope, enter into a tedious Harrangue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Neceſſity and Unavoidableneſs of Death, nor uſe many Arguments to convince you that your <hi>Earthly Tabernacles ſhall be diſſolved:</hi> Your own Experience is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to perſwade you to the belief of it, there being hardly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105264:5"/> any Houſe or Family in the Country which hath not ſome Buried out of it; you dayly ſee your Friends Expiring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Faces: You are preſent at the Cloſing of their Eyes, and attend them after to their Graves. The Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bells, and the Mourners about the ſtreets, the frequent Lamentations of Wives for their Husbands, and Children for their Parents, and Friends for the loſs of their Relations, are a ſufficient Evidence of the Triumphs of Death over all Ages, all Sexes, and all Conditions. Or if theſe do not convince you, of the declining ſtate of your Mortal Tabernacles, yet caſt your Eyes I beſeech you on that diſmal Spectacle that hath aſſembled you together, and now lies before your Eyes, as the Spoil and Conqueſt of the King of Terrors. He was once as freſh and active as any of you that pay this Charitable Office to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, but behold he now lyes as an uſeleſs and unactive lump of Clay, without any other uſe or ſignification than that of a Deaths Head, to put you all in mind of your own mortallity. In his Fate you ought to conſider the uncertainty of your own condition; and from the view of his Senſleſs and Unactive Body, to reflect upon the frailty of your own, and ſo to number your Days, that you may apply your Hearts to that true Wiſdom, which alone will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſupport you at the laſt. For this is the true end and deſign of Funerals, which were not ſo much intended for the Commendation of the Deceaſed, as the Information and Inſtruction of the Living: and ſo much <hi>Solomon</hi> hath told us, Eccleſ. 7. 2. <hi>It is better to go to the Houſe of Mourning, than to go to the Houſe of Feaſting, for that is the end of all Men, and the Living will lay it to his Heart:</hi> That is, they ought to be ſeriouſly affected with it, and awakened to prepare themſelves for Death.</p>
            <p>3. I now proceed to the <hi>3d.</hi> Particular or Obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi> That after the Diſſolution of theſe Frail Bodies they ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105264:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105264:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105264:7"/> be advanced to a ſtate of Immortality: So the Apoſtle tells us in my Text, <hi>That after this Earthly Tabernacle is Diſsolv'd, we have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens;</hi> And this will be made good from Two Conſiderations. Firſt from the Texts of Scripture that affirm it: Secondly from Natural Reaſon to enſorce it.</p>
            <p>If we conſult the Scriptures we ſhall find them plain and decretory in the point: Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 42. That it is ſown in Corruption, but raiſed in Incorruption: That this Corruptible ſhall put on Incorruption, and this Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſhall put on Immortallity,</hi> verſ. 53, 54. And in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. 'tis his expreſs Affirmation, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt ſhall change our Vile Body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his Glorious Body according to the mighty working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things unto himſelf.</hi> Now if our Bodies in the Reſurrection muſt be like unto our Saviours, it will then follow that they muſt be advanced to a ſtate of Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſince his was ſo after his Reſurrection; for ſo the Scriptures affirm concerning him; <hi>Chriſt being raiſed from the Dead dyeth no more, Death hath no more dominion over him,</hi> Rom. 6. 9.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Natural Reaſon may come in for the proof of this particular; Reaſon is able to inform us of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing poſtulatums to prove the truth of it.</p>
            <p>1. That a Reſurrection in general is not impoſſible. To him that believes that there is a God, it is more eaſie to convince him of the poſſibility of a Reſurrection than of the contrary; for it is founded on the Power and the Will of God; to the former of which nothing is impoſſible; and he has no reaſon to doubt the latter, if God had any where revealed his Intentions concerning it.</p>
            <p>2. That it is no impoſſible thing to make a Body immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſince it is no more than the deveſting it of its corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105264:7"/> Qualities, and arraying it again with a freſher Luſtre; 'Tis only done by taking away the Internal Principle, that inclines it to Corruption, and placing in its ſtead a Seed and a Principle of Incorruption; and he that thinks this impoſſible to an Omnipotent Power muſt have very mean and diſhonourable thoughts of the Power of God.</p>
            <p>3. That it is highly equitable, that the ſame Numerical Body ſhould be raiſed again that once lived upon the Earth, that, as it has been a Partner with the Soul, in doing Good or Evil in this life, ſo it may again partake a ſhare of its good or bad fortune in the life to come: We do all know that the Body is the great Inſtrument of the Soul, by which ſhe acts and exerts her Operations, that it is fitted with Organs for the performance of them; That as it is the Unhappy Parent of moſt of the Sins that we commit, ſo it is a neceſſary Inſtrument for the diſcharge of ſeveral commendable Virtues; ſuch as Faſting and Temperance, Sobriety, and Chaſtity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And would it not be the moſt abſurd and unreaſonable thing in the World, to Puniſh one Body for the Sins committed in another; to have one worn out with Paleneſs and Mortification, and another ſnatch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way its Reward.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Argument that <hi>Tertullian</hi> inſiſts on<note place="margin">De Reſurrect. Cap. 56.</note> to prove the Reſurection of the ſame body, <hi>Quam abſurdum, quam Ethnicum, utrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> autem quam Deo indignum aliam ſubſtantiam operari, aliam mercede di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpungi, ut hoec quidem caro Matyrio lanietur, alia vero coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur: Nonne preſtat omnem ſemel fidem, a ſpe reſurrectionis abducere, quam de gravitate at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> juſtitia Dei ludere, Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pro Valentino reſuſſitati.</hi> 'Tis a thing unbecoming the Juſtice of God to oblige one ſubſtance to Toyl and Labour, and give away its Recompence to another: That one body ſhould ſuffer the pains of Martyrdom for the ſake of Chriſt, and another ſhall receive the Crown that never labour'd for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105264:8"/> it, and it were much better to Deny the Article of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, than ſo to Sport with the Wiſdom and the Juſtice of God, as to ſuppoſe him to raiſe up <hi>Marcion</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Valentinius</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. That where God has declared his Mind that he will do ſo, and we have no juſt reaſon to doubt that it his will to have it ſo; 'tis then highly reaſonable to believe that it ſhall be ordered according to his Will: Now all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are agreed, That the Scriptures do contain the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Divine Will, that God has therein made a diſcovery of his Intentions, as to the future ſtate of our Souls and Bodies: And ſince we have an account given us in thoſe Scriptures, that God will raiſe them to a State of Honour and Immortality, we have no reaſon to diſtruſt either the poſſibility of the thing, or the actual performance of it, in its due and appointed ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now deſcend to the Conſideration of thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars that remain, but I muſt paſs them by at preſent, and ſhow you what uſe you are to make of what has been already diſcourſed unto you: I ſhall only name the Heads and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt. This may inform us of the indiſpenſible neceſſity of ſo ordering all our Affairs in this Life, as perſons that expect to be called to an account for them in the next; if it be ſo that after Death our Bodies muſt again be raiſed out of the Duſt, and entred into a ſtate of Eternal Joy or Pain, and if every Man muſt receive the things done in his Body, according to that he has done, whether it be good or bad, <hi>what manner of perſons ought we to be in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Converſation and Godlineſs, looking for, and haſtening to the coming of our Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105264:8"/>
            <p>Secondly, This ſhould learn us not to abuſe theſe Bodies of ours by Riot or Intemperance, by Adultery or Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for if they muſt be raiſed again to a ſtate of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; is it any wiſdom in us to treat them at that rate, as if we were never more to ſee them or enjoy them: Do we act like prudent and conſidering perſons? like Men that wiſh well to thoſe Bodies we ſeem ſo fond of? as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulph them in a ſtate of endleſs and irremediable ſorrows.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It may inſtruct us farther in the neceſſity and advantage of a patient Submiſſion to the Will of Heaven, whenſoever any Sharp Pains, or Accute Diſeaſes are ſent upon our Bodies, knowing that theſe Diſtempers will not laſt for ever; that they are ſent from Heaven with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Kindneſs to wean us from the World, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent our falling into that place of Torments from whence there is no Redemption: We ought therefore to bear with patience all thoſe Pains that Arreſt our Bodies; For as our own Sins have pull'd them upon our Heads, ſo our Repentance may make them the ſalutary Inſtruments of our Reformation. We may comfort our ſelves in the midſt of our Agonies with the Reflections of repoſing them, and our Bodies together in our Beds of Duſt, and that how crazy ſoever and diſordered they may be in this life we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them again in an improved condition, like a Totter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Houſe pull'd down to the ground that it may be re edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed to for better advantage.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Conſiderations with which every one of us may entertain our Thoughts, in the midſt of Infirmities, and Acute Diſtempers; and with ſuch Reflections as theſe, I doubt not, but this Reverend Deceaſed Prelate did enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf in the intervalls of his Sickneſs, till the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of an Appoplexy diſcompoſed his Reaſon, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105264:9"/> rendered all farther Meditation uſeleſs to his Expiring Soul.</p>
            <p>And now that he has ſubmitted to the Laws of Death, and is become a Captive to the King of Terrors, it will I preſume be deſired by ſome, and expected by moſt that are preſent at this Mournful Solemnity, that ſome ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhould be given of his Life and Actions, who had the peculiar Talent of Concealing Himſelf, and of being known to None ſo well as to God and His own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and happy is that Man who can ſo order his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the whole Courſe of his Life and Converſation, as to have them approved by his own Conſcience, and to be able to appear with Confidence at the Tribunal of the Searcher of Hearts, whatſoever Cenſures and Opinions the vain World may either make or entertain of them: 'Tis the Affirmation of St. <hi>John, That if our Hearts condem us not, then have we Confidence towards God;</hi> we need not fear that he will lay any thing to our Charge that we are not guilty of, but may appear before him with a modeſt Aſſurance of his Approbation of all that is good in us, and of his Pardon for theſe Infirmities which we could not help.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not pretend to give you an exact and entire Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Life and Actions, which have been ſo much in the View and Obſervation of the World, by the ſeveral Eminent Stations that he has paſſed through in the Church, but ſhall only confine my ſelf to ſome ſhort and imperfect hints, and leave the reſt to the Sober Reflections of ſuch as were his Intimates and Familiars. He was Born in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire</hi> in the Year 1629, and Educated in the Free-Shool of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> where he made ſuch early and nimble advances in Gramaticall Learning, that by Thirteen Years of Age he was fit to be Admitted into <hi>Emanuel</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> A Society Famous for the Education of Men of Parts and Learning, and happy in Three of its Members, Men
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105264:9"/> of Great Learning and Fiety, of Great Prudence and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Bedle,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> together with the Late, and Preſent, Moſt Reverend ArchBiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> from thence he was Elected into a Fellowſhip in <hi>Gonvill</hi> and <hi>Caius</hi> Colledge, in which Society he continued till the Reſtoration of the Royall Family, applying himſelf with ſo much Induſtry and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Knowledge of all the ſeveral parts of Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Learning, that (if I am not mis-informed in my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts) he obtained the Reputation of a good Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, an excellent Crittick in the Greek Tongue, and was looked on as one of the moſt Eminent Perſons of his Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Univerſity:</p>
            <p>He was well skill'd in the Old, and the New, the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotelian</hi> and <hi>Cartefian</hi> Phyloſophy; and as he took a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular fancy to the <hi>Platonick</hi> and the <hi>Stoical</hi> Phyloſophy, the one tending to the Explication of the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Inſtitutions, and the other to the Reformation of the Immoral Lives of the Heathen World; ſo he had fully Imbibed all the Principles that thoſe Inſtitutions could inſtruct him in, and gave a convincing Evidence of the Power of thoſe Principles, and the Influence they had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the great Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Mind, and the Moderation and Undiſturbed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Paſſions: No man ever yet ſaw him Angry at any Injury or Affront that was offered him, nor Diſturbed in his Thoughts by any croſs Accidents that came in his way, but he remained Unmoved, like a Rock in the midſt of Angry Billows, they only broke themſelves into Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by Daſhing on the Outward Man, but could make no Impreſſion on a Mind that contemned the exterior Blaſts of Fortune, and underſtood the Art of Calming the Force, and Moderating the Impetus of them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105264:10"/>
            <p>In the Year 1660 he was Invited into <hi>Ireland</hi> by that great Maſter of Parts and Learning, of Eloquence and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, the late Reverend Pious and Learned Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor;</hi> a Perſon that had all the Requiſites and all the Indowments of a Schollar and a Gentleman, a Great Phyloſopher, and an Excellent Divine, a Sublime Wit, and an Admirable Preacher; and had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the advantage of ſo Obliging a Converſation, that as one (that knew him well) affirmed of his Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they had all the Pleaſantneſs of a Comedy, and all the Uſefulneſs of a Sermon: This was that Great and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Man that firſt Invited your Dioceſan into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and I take it to be no ſmall Character and Advantage to this Deceaſed Perſon, that ſo Great a Maſter of Learning, ſo Exemplary a Perſon for Devotion, ſo Wiſe a Diſcerner of Spirits, and ſo Able a Judge of the Abilities of Others, did pitch upon your Departed Archbiſhop as a Perſon worthy of his Care and Favour: By him he was firſt Admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Orders of Deacon and Prieſt, as if he had thereby a fatidical and preſaging Spirit of the growing hopes of that Plant which he had firſt planted in the Lords Vineyard.</p>
            <p>And as it is natural to all Husbandmen, to intend the cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivation of that Plant which anſwers their Pains and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, ſo he ſoon afetr procured his Advancement to the Deanary of <hi>Connor,</hi> from whence, by the Unexpected Kindneſs of the Lord Chancellor <hi>Hide,</hi> he was Removed to the Deanary of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> and had a Patent ſent him for it out of <hi>England</hi> without any ſeeking or application of his own. In this Dignity he continued diſcharging the Office of a Dignatary and a Private Miniſter, with all Faithfulneſs and Diligence, till in the Year 1667 he was Advanced to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lymrick,</hi> from whence, by gentle and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſteps, he was removed to <hi>Kilmore</hi> and <hi>Ardagh,</hi> and at laſt to the Dignity of a Metropolitan in this Province: And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105264:10"/> all theſe Promotions fell upon him (as he affirmed) he knew not how, otherwiſe than by the <hi>Providence</hi> of God, and the <hi>Kindneſs</hi> of his Freinds, that negotiated his Removals with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his application for them.</p>
            <p>'Tis an argument of an Extraordinary Providence, as well as of great Merit, that Preferments drop into the mouths of ſome, when others are forced to court like Coy Miſtriſſes, and after all meet with Diſappointment; But you have had the honour of an Archbiſhop that has been rather courted by Preſerments than a Soliciter of them, which ought therefore to give a due Value and Eſteem to his Memory and Reputation.</p>
            <p>I need not put you in mind of his Actions and Behaviour in ſo publick a Theater of Promotion, you are all witneſſes of them as well as my ſelf, and are able to contradict any Narrative, that is not founded upon the greateſt Candour and Veracity; you know that he has walked, according to the Character of the Apoſtle, <hi>by Evil Report and Good Report,</hi> that ſome of his moſt innocent Actions have had the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be miſrepreſented; and thô it is not poſſible for Men in his Eminent Station to walk with ſo much Caution, but that ſome one or other ſhall blame their Conduct, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a Cenſorious Age, and among a Buſie People, that are more Ready to enquire into the Miſcarriages of others, than Reform their own; and who, like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> ſpend their time either in Telling or Hearing ſome New thing, yet this I will be bold to Affirm, becauſe I know the Truth of it, That no Man was more willing to retract an Error when told of it, nor more thankful to his Monitor, than he was.</p>
            <p>And if a Man may make an eſtimate of his Love of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and his reall deſire of advancing and rewarding it in others, by the Choice of his Chaplains, no Man in his Station, could make a more prudent choice, nor perform it with more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105264:11"/> frankneſs and generoſity, for he courted them to it with out their own interceſſion for it. For being well verſed in Eccleſiaſtical Antiquity, and having obſerved the Lives and Behaviour of the Primitive Biſhops, how ready they were to advance the Glory of God, and promote theſe to Officers in the Curch, whom they beleived moſt likely to carry on that deſigne after their Death; He Reſolved to conform himſelf to ſo Glorious a Preſident, and make their Examples a Pattern for his Imitation.</p>
            <p>Nor was he leſs Remarkable for his Charity to the Poor, then his love of Learning; many Indigent Perſons partake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Bounty, without knowing the Hand from whence it came, and diſpencing it with that Secreſie and prudent Caution, that his Left Hand knew not what his Right Hand did. He was loath to looſe the Reward of a Good Action by making it Pompous and Theatrical, and thought it more valluable to receive the Approbation of God, and the Applauſe of Men and Angels, than the Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Men in this life.</p>
            <p>I need not mention his great Temperance and Abſtemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the midſt of a Plentifull Table, and a Luxurious Age, leaſt it ſhould ſeem a ſilent Reproof of that Riot and Debauchery that too much reigns among us, and for which we have ſo lately been ſcourged by the Hand of God. An Abſtinence ſo much the more commendable, becauſe it ſeem'd to be done in Imitation of the Ancient <hi>Eremites,</hi> that fed upon Roots and Hearbs, preferring them before the greateſt Dainties; it was the putting a Knife to his Throat, in the Phraſe of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and a voluntary act of Penance, and Mortification upon himſelf: A mighty and convincing evidence of ſelf Denyall, and an argument of his maſtery over his Appetite, that he could reſtrain its motions at a ſeaſon, when Pleaſures and Temptations invited to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105264:11"/>
            <p>Shall I mention it as an argument of his Peaceable Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he abhored Controverſies and Suits of Law, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to Remit ſomething of his Right, then to be Vexatious and Uneaſy to himſelf and others. That he followed the things that made for Peace, and choſe rather to prevent and cloſe a Breach, then ſuffer the Wound to ſeſter and rankle by an unſeaſonable oppoſition; that he was of a moſt Compaſſionate and Reſenting Diſpoſition, being not only willing to Pitty and Releive the Neceſſities of his wanting Brethren: But beſides that, full of Indulgence and Compaſſion to his Tenants, in making them conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Abatements for their ſufferings by the Calamities of the Times.</p>
            <p>Theſe my Brethren, and ſeveral other Inſtances that I could give, of his Regular and conſtant Devotions in his Family, of his Liberality in adorning of his Epiſcopall Pallace, of his great Humility and Affability, are an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a rare and an excellent Spirit, and a fit preſident for the Imitation of others. And now that our <hi>Elias</hi> is taken up into Heaven, and ſtands no more in need of our Prayers, or our Wiſhes, let us all joyn in an united Prayer to God, that a double Portion of his Spirit may deſcend upon his Succeſſor, when he ſhall be Inveſted with his Robe and Mantle; That ſo he may, not only Imitate him in every thing that is comendable, but be a wholeſome pattern to the Flock of Chriſt which he has purchaſed with the ſhedding of his Blood. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
